This story began with a chance
train encounter on New Year's Eve.
Santa Claus was
going home from the war.
I've come from serious places,
where there's combat,
to visit the kids
and wish them a Happy New Year.
For myself, I'd wish...
probably for peace to begin
and for this war to end.
- I'll be in touch!
- Send it to me, OK?
Yes, yes, yes.
His name was llya.
To my surprise, llya turned out to be
a Ukrainian fighting on Russia's side.
We exchanged numbers
and agreed to be in touch.
Happy New Year, Moscow!-
Glory to Heroes of Russia! -
I didn't expect this war.
I thought that after losing so many lives to conflict,
we Russians would finally find our wars consigned to history.
But it's almost a year
since Russia invaded Ukraine.
Almost a year since the shock
of waking as citizens of a warring state.
And today, my compatriots in uniform
look on from these posters.
Who are these guys?
In Russian media, they're heroes
who always win and never die.
In the West, they're war criminals,
reigning terror and destruction.
The fog of war is so thick you barely
see the human stories it's made of.
llya's story, a Ukrainian in Russian
uniform, was the first thread I could pull.
- I'm waiting!
And l'll return!
Promise?
- I promise.
Alive, most importantly...
Alive, of course, baby.
- And not wounded!
- Alive, of course, baby.
And not wounded!
I'll try not to get wounded.
Once more!
Not over the doorstep.
In 200 metres, turn right.
For me, the war didn't start in 2022.
It started in 2014.
That was the beginning
of the civil war, roughly speaking, in Ukraine.
I lost my home, I lost my business.
Basically, they took it all.
That was when
I parted ways with Ukraine.
- Kiev Railway Station, Moscow -
All will be well.
We just have to fight a bit more.
I didn't fully understand llya's story then.
But when he called from the front,
I begged to join him.
I'm here completely unofficially.
I'm going at my own risk, of course.
Without Defence Ministry permission.
Without Defence Ministry permission
Not even press accreditation.
I'm interested...
It's no idle interest, but an attempt
to understand what's going on...
With my country.
bridge inscription: Dedicated to the
Eternal Russian-Ukrainian Friendship -
This is the 'Lugansk People's Republic.'
This is the 'Lugansk People's Republic.
Or 'occupied Eastern Ukraine.'
Or 'new Russian territories.'
It depends who you ask.
I was sure l'd be sent back,
maybe even arrested.
But trying isn't torture.
I introduced myself to the command,
and said I'm making a documentary,
about different fates in this war and
I was interested in filming some soldiers.
Well, first they allowed it, then forbade it,
then allowed it again, then...
...well, it's not clear.
The battalion's in the rear temporarily,
180km from the front.
For now, the supply unit
has adopted me.
Here's a uniform for you too.
There's nothing smaller.
They gave me a sleeping bag, boots
and a uniform so I wouldn't stand out.
Whose house is this?
It was offered to us by a local granny.
She doesn't live here.
Well, she tends to the garden.
So they just gave you the house?
Yes. So you could say
we're having a nice rest here.
We don't have many personnel
left from previous battles...
so now they're adding new people.
As soon as the unit's replenished,
back to the front.
Several battalions are stationed
temporarily in this village.
Anastasia, they're here.
The guys are taking food
to friends coming from the front.
Anastasia, this is the 1st battalion,
what's left of it.
Out of 900, only 300 remain, right?
- Honestly, I don't even remember.
- You don't remember?
The survivors are left.
As they say...
we are ill-fated.
We...
I'll just get my brains together.
I have!
- They dumped us there.
- We were dumped and got surrounded.
We didn't know how to get out of there.
We took the first fire fight, just a bit...
Just a bit.
There! I even have tears. Fuck.
To be honest, we were
attacked pretty fucking badly.
How
of us came back?
many
Out of 900, just 300 people.
Half of them are crippled.
And in these seven months...
Oh, fuck! I forgot to tell
someone stole my left brain hemisphere.
We searched all night but didn't find it.
I was told at the hospital that
my left brain hemisphere was stolen.
Because of that, my left arm
doesn't work, and my left leg limps.
Do you have family? Kids?
No, I'm divorced.
And what is our fate?
No family.
Kids? Well, there are,
but you can say, not.
My contract ended on February 7th.
All of ours on the 7th.
His in January, can you believe it?
What can you do? Fuck all!
What do they tell you?
To the trenches!
Go back?
They want to send you back?
- Are you able to go back?
-No.
Anastasia, what are you filming?
- A documentary.
It's about us. With the truth.
Not like on TV, but the truth.
- Star: equips you with knowledge
Anastasia, never believe
what they show on TV.
They don't just lie, they bullshit.
llya's battalion has only 80 people left out of 400.
To make up for losses, 300 'newbies' were added.
Most were drafted,
and have no military experience.
was surprised that some
followed someone voluntarily,
a father with a son,
or a friend with a friend.
Smarty, bring everyone here.
We're coming!
Wait, we're warming up.
OK, let's go.
Who's shooting?
Over here.
They're already loaded.
20 people willing to shoot.
20 people who want to shoot.
CMBHAR
BOAK
When you're above,
controlling the drone,
you look at all the people,
they're so small. Defenceless.
lam the eyes and ears of my comrades.
My callsign is Cap.
I'm here because I followed
my friend voluntarily, I wasn't drafted.
He's just, 'Cartoon'.
He and I, we're like,
best friends since childhood.
Before the draft,
I didn't think about it at all.
Then, when my call-up came through,
I kind of sat, thought about it,
and decided that I had to go.
After all, my family...
I want them all to be alive and well.
What's the threat to your family?
What do you fight for?
Nazism!
Most of all, Nazism. I hate it.
Because...
People, they're all the same.
It doesn't matter what nation,
or what religion, we're all people!
And then there are Nazis.
I just hate them.
- You think there's a lot here in Ukraine?
- Yes.
Here, the majority of
Ukrainian people hate Russians.
But why, I just can't understand.
How do you know they hate Russians?
Well, from the fact that the war started.
First of all, I came here
to fight for my friend, Cartoon.
And secondly, I want
revenge for my dead comrades
Three classmates died.
Of course, it's bad, but I want revenge.
- Vitaly, do we light a fire?
Unlike the newly drafted, the supply unit
is almost entirely volunteers.
I don't know about you, but I fight
for my women. So they live well.
Fucking bullshit.
You're 50, alone,
and have nothing, damn it.
You're not here for a woman.
Then for whom?
- For yourself.
To profit and to shit.
Fuck!
For sluts and alcohol.
Vitaly!
I've been here for eight months, bro.
Eight months.
So?
It's a shame you don't have a woman.
Yuri, I had a woman. I've told you.
She said I won't go back,
that I'd be killed.
00:16:58,800 --> 00:16:58,320
that l'd be killed.
She said. I won't go back,
That was it, we broke up.
I left her a two-bedroom flat!
For her kid.
Fuck me!
I'm very happy that
there are people like you!
I'm not like that, and so what?
Yura, you're an old fool.
Because your women are golddiggers.
But they text me.
You're not here for Russia or patriotism
but for money, so you can waste it later.
Yes, exactly that, Vitaly.
- Well, it's dumb.
And why are you here?
- Me?
I told you why I'm here.
Once again.
I came here for patriotism.
Do you see it?
Not anymore, unfortunately.
I'm so sorry for you, Vitaly.
Because, in that, you're not alone here.
You're not alone here, Vitaly.
OK, where's the moonshine?
You say 'gorilka', right?
Gorilka, gorilka.
- In Ukrainian.
00:18:12,865 --> 00:18:12,240
- Gorilka, gorilka.
Pour it on the table.
There, it's burning already.
- I don't like that smell.
I'm already drunk.
First of all, I want to drink
to the boys fighting here with us.
Those who are here.
And those who will join us.
As for the war,
what are we fighting for here?
I'll tell you simply...
Here, everyone has the same motive.
Say 'money' and I'll kill you.
Money!
Money 100%. It's 100% money. But!
You're wrong.
- But! But...
Why deny that we all have
our own motivation?
Why impose that one?
I don't get you 50-year-old men,
who only think about
money, money, money!
Where will you take it all, to your grave?
Is money really the most important thing?
Of course it's not!
You have no one to feed.
You don't have shit, so you talk this way.
Well, I have someone to feed!
Can I say...
- Tell us your point of view.
My oldest is 16 now. Right?
-OK.
- The next is army age in 4 years.
- Get to the point!
Wait. Let me finish!
Let me finish.
If I and all my friends don't go today,
my kids will tomorrow.
So I came today...
So I came today, so that tomorrow,
my kids don't have to.
I thought I was fighting for our country.
And why are you here?
- Yes, why?
- I'll tell you.
Make it beautiful.
was a drug addict.
Fuckin ‘eh!
- I went crazy.
I was fucking crazy.
I just know I'd have been sucked back in
if I hadn't come here.
I have just one question. May I ask?
To Volodya.
Why doesn't Volodya...
value the term 'patriotism'?
Why?
No idea.
-What the fuck!
-Be quiet!
Patriotism exists, but...
I don't know.
Let's be quick.
Don't slow down.
I don't know.
Yes.
Bitch!
Fucking hell.
Why?
What do you think?
There, over by the boxes.
And that's my bed.
And a young commander,
with his head bashed in,
was carried out.
it's very scary.
Calm down, do you hear?
Why?
I need to know...
If I'm caught in a fight,
I always need to know that I'm right.
If I'm wrong, I don't fight.
That's how it is here.
Yes, that's it here.
We got into a fight with Ukraine,
but I don't feel I'm right.
There...
This is how we self-medicate.
For victory.
We'll see how it all ends.
But I think the losses will be huge.
Today, the whole battalion
is leaving for the front.
Surprisingly, command has
tolerated me in the rear so far.
But I'm going...
so I don't upset the command...
a bit secretly from them.
If they don't catch me
before we leave, of course.
This all has to be filmed.
I'll try as hard as I can to minimize
consequences for the participants.
To try to tell the story and do no harm.
We'll see how it ends.
Mechanics, drivers, spotters, operators.
Are you loaded?
Almost.
Where's Cap? Cap, my brother!
So we're leaving right now?
Leave everything and go as we are?
Guys, wave for the camera, please.
You beauties!
In today's video, you will see
how Russian military personnel travel.
The world's second strongest army.
Imagine how it is in the fourth!
Not knowing where to.
Nothing changes.
It's the same as 30 years ago.
Girl, stop! Don't!
Don't confuse one dance with another.
Anechka, I'm not drinking.
I need my cat.
cat.
A cat?
Yes, where is she?
Here somewhere.
She's under the table.
You don't get it.
No cat means no luck.
Musya, let's go.
You've been here long enough.
Musya, sit.
Musya, sit quietly.
Watch it, you have to sit on all that stuff.
Are they waiting for us?
In theory, yes.
I don't know how they drive.
We're advancing in all directions:
tanks, infantry, artillery fire.
We're killed but we survive.
And again,
we throw ourselves into attack.
Lena, I'm busy, I can't talk.
Cheers to life, war be damned...
We've stopped on the way to the front.
We sleep in a Soviet nuclear bunker.
We can't stay here long.
We've no choice. That's it for now.
- Everything created by
the people must be protected -
The move takes two days.
Everything here feels like a Soviet time capsule.
- Civil Defence's role: defend the people
against weapons of mass destruction -
The people who created the USSR,
must be turning in their graves now,
because it's all been destroyed.
It even came to war.
After the collapse of the Soviet Union
a confrontation began
between Eastern and Western Ukraine.
All the heritage that united us was
being destroyed by Western nationalists:
demolishing statues of Soviet heroes,
rewriting textbooks, renaming of streets.
If we speak Russian, we're like
second class Ukrainians to them.
But for me, the ties between
Russia and Eastern Ukraine
transcend all borders that
appeared after the collapse of the USSR.
We are for peace!
Glory to Labour! -
- Glory to Labour! -
Long Live Soviet Trade Unions:
the School of Communism!-
- Discipline and organisation
are the law for everyone! -
I just remember how
we lived together before.
Russia and Ukraine
were always inseparable.
That brotherly Union, I miss it.
I see these destroyed houses.
And those poor people
with no electricity, gas, or water.
It's awful.
I know what it's like.
The "dill" [slur for Ukrainians] bombed my house.
I'd go in, look at the rubble,
and I just didn't have
the will to do anything.
I'd sit for an hour thinking...
About how it could
have been avoided 10 times.
And about how we're at war
with ourselves.
Slavs against Slavs.
It turns out that some Slavs
are for the West,
and some Slavs are for Russia.
We reached our new base.
It's a small town 7km from the front.
The first one went.
The second went!
Where's it going?
There, against the wall.
Wait, they want to park
the Urals [trucks] there.
Why are you standing around? Help us!
Put something under the wheel!
Move, fuck!
Back the truck up here.
You're on guard, I'm going.
Come on, Leha, slowly!
The battalion medics come for fuel.
They explain that Code 300 means
'wounded' and Code 200 - 'dead.'
We'll hear these terms often.
The evacuation point is where
soldiers are dropped off to find their trenches,
and where the dead and wounded
are left to be retrieved by the medics.
- Anyone here?
- Hello.
Coming with us?
Will you go with us?
- I am going there.
- There?
OK, let's go. I must find a dude.
You didn't see a body there?
Fucking close.
This way? OK, I'll go this way then.
And you go that way.
He must be here somewhere.
If you see a crater, check if he's in there.
Where are you, bro? Give me a sign.
Got him?
Great.
OK, bro, thanks.
It's flying everywhere!
- We know!
OK, bro, we've come for you. Be cool.
So heavy, brother.
Hell.
Sit down, fuck.
Fucking bitches.
Fuck
all.
Fuck you all.
He's the battalion's first death, a 'newbie.'
No one even had a chance
to get to know him.
Girls, thank you all, you're heroes.
Looks like a stomach wound.
He has nothing on him!
Just a knife and flashlight.
Well, Nastia, fuck.
I tell you, he has no papers.
They said there are. Look carefully.
His inner pockets.
I don't know, maybe he has...
pockets in his sweater?
Here are the 'Girls Like Stars.' Fuck!
'Stars like her!'
- A fucking turn.
-'Like her!'
Nope! No documents.
Gerda, heating isn't the best idea now.
Girls, like stars,
shine in the sky till dawn.
I could fall in love with one,
once and forever, with ease.
Is there a tag at least?
Stars like her.
Girls like stars.
Damn! I always smell it from afar, fuck.
There's a tag.
Want me to open it?
The face, yes.
What do the guys die for?
But to take someone over...
What the fuck is the point?
What will it change?
Will the war stop?
Now that's history, fuck!
Our ancestors and descendants
will know about this.
What will they think of this shit?
I mean... Fuck!
Ukraine, it's a very beautiful country.
It's like Russia, I can say.
grew up in a shabby
square like this at Granny's.
But this fucking war,
it just ruins everything.
I love our motherland.
Russia is my motherland.
Although for me, motherland
begins and ends with my comrades.
- People live here -
I recall, at about 7, telling my parents,
'I want to be in the military.'
They asked, 'What about a family?'
\ I said, 'Fuck it.'
Comrades are family for me
and I don't need anything more.
Russia is the traditions
and values we grew up with! -
- The world's not crap, people are! -
Whoever wrote this
is fucking Confucius!
O8
DA
Let's roll.
I didn't tell anyone that I left, nope.
But while our boys are here,
I'll go nowhere. How could I leave them?
Pigs! Throw your garbage in the can! -
Danger to life [in Ukrainian]
You got through?
There's no reception.
Enough!
- Those who persevere, win -
I've never climbed
abandoned buildings like this.
They probably wanted
to build apartments here.
Hello? Hi sunshine.
Did you fix your broken nail?
That's sad.
I'm listening.
I'm listening to you.
Go on, tell me!
Whatever comes to mind.
This is my first time
on the roof of a nine-story building.
How beautiful!
It's breathtaking.
Where do they keep firing?
Just into the void...
Naturally, we'll all lose someone here.
Boom!
That was loud.
There's zero information.
No one really knows anything.
- Your first time heading to the front too?
- Yeah.
Watch for birds [drones].
Some fucking silence.
Watch for birds [drones).
Watch for birds (drones].
Watch for birds [drones])
Calm before the storm.
We have to go up to the trenches.
Yes, we need to climb this mountain.
Speed up, guys.
OK, from here. No point going higher.
Look, be careful with the pin.
Slowly!
Why's it so tight?
OK, ready. I can launch.
OK, guys, we're flying.
Cap, Cap, this is Cartoon. Come in
Cap, Cap, this is Cartoon. Come in.
We'll stop and wait.
I'm expecting him back from a mission.
It's his first outing. I've already been.
Cap, this is Cartoon. Come in.
- Cap here.
Where are you, bro?
Heading for the school
from the nine-story building.
Roger.
Look how clean he is!
My brother!
Look here.
What is it?
I took shrapnel.
- Peace, bro.
Shrapnel?
My partner's a dickhead.
- What did he do?
We loaded up the drone grenades,
took off, and his dropped right away.
I see them fall and turn away.
It goes off, and a shrapnel
shard splits both my lips.
- Was your camera always on?
- I hung it here on my chest.
OK,here.
OK, guys, we'll take off.
- This shrapnel fucked me up.
Sorry.
- Alive? OK?
- Yes.
Grab it all and let's get out of here.
Most importantly, we still have balls.
Run,run.
The medics poured me a shot.
I said, 'Fuck off with your vodka!'
Shit, you're shaking.
- My teeth still hurt.
Of course.
Let's go home.
If it had been a bit higher!
Imagine if it hit my temple.
Fuck! Code 200 and you're home.
Remember, in the summer,
before we got here?
Before we were drafted.
A wasp stung my lip,
remember the photo?
Yes! Botox.
A fucking lip like that!
Botox.
Tire. Tire. Reply to Amin.
Find out the nature of the wound.
Amin, this is Tire.
Shrapnel near the heart, over.
Understood, over.
Chief, there's a war on!
You're too gentle with the van.
We'll fix it.
That's it, stop.
- Enough!
- That's it.
Put something under my head!
Let's go!
Be patient, brother.
How are you feeling?
- OK. It really hurts, fuck.
Chief, drive carefully! But fast, damn!
Be patient, please, just a little longer.
Your arm's tattooed! You never told me.
Cannula!
Master, they took him, he left.
It's OK, brother, it'll be fine.
My son isn't in school yet,
I can't die now.
You're lucky.
Yeah. A few centimetres lower
and you'd be out of luck.
Give me a cigarette.
You're not allowed brother.
- I want to fucking smoke.
- OK.
- Don't follow me, I'm lost myself. -
You've heard that Russian troops
were accused of war crimes?
A war crime?
War crimes. That civilians were killed,
people were r****.
- What do you think, is it true?
- I think it's not true.
It couldn't happen?
It couldn't happen.
Well, I've seen lots of people.
Many.
Some are capable of a lot.
But to go up to civilians
who've done nothing to you,
and kill them, r*** them, bury them?
No, Russian troops couldn't do that,
they wouldn't. Why would they?
People just live their lives.
Why ruin that person's life?
But we invaded their country?
We kind of invaded..
Maybe not of our own free will.
00:52:44,545 --> 00:52:44,160
We kind of invaded...
There was an order.
We went in.
You think the order was right?
Cap, do you have a 7.62?
- Check my jacket. Left pocket.
- What are you doing?
- Adding the bullet...
What are you doing?
to my tag.
Just a memento.
A memento.
I'd get it if it had come out of your chest
- You want a bullet in my chest?
- No.
That's that then.
It's broken.
Let's test it now.
Of course...
Fucking hell!
That was dangerous, fuck.
We should all be 200
and sent home by now.
Done!
That's all. It drops, pierces the capsule...
- Where's the tailpiece from?
- The guys rigged it.
I just need to refine this nail mechanism.
Where did I put that little drill bit?
For the uninitiated, what's it for?
To kill.
How right is all this?
What do I think?
What should I think? Tell me.
- What exactly?
All of it, making drone grenades to...
- I'd say...
it's either me or them.
Well, I'm doing this for myself,
to survive.
You ask such questions,
I don't even know how to answer them.
Have you thought about it?
- What should I think about?
That we're on their land and we
should turn around and fuck off?
Leave our guys on their own?
Is that what we should have done?
Being on their land. Invading.
And them bombing their own people
for eight years is nothing?
How many children died?
And old men and women.
They bombed their own people.
We're a bit wrong, they're a bit wrong.
For sure, that's what it is.
I'm just doing my job right now.
Oh shit.
Shit, I broke the drill bit.
Damn! I glued my fingers together.
- From Cartoon to Cap,
together to the end, brother -
Mario! Come on, fuck.
Fucking volunteers.
Tourists.
We're not in the military now.
You go there often?
Humanitarian aid from the 'great'
United Russia Party doesn't get there.
So the medics take it.
It's a beautiful village.
26 people.
They're bombing there now?
Yes. The Commander asked why the fuck
are we, idiots, going there.
Somewhere round here, by a blue gate.
This whole war is like
stagnant gonorrhoea.
It's neither here nor there.
Where to?
I'll sit down and organise it.
Fellow villagers are so happy!
I go out at 8 am
and the boxes are waiting.
'Where's this from?'
I say, soldiers brought it.
Amin, report to Yamal's location.
We need to remove shrapnel
from a leg, over.
Your truck's no good.
That '300', are they alive or wounded?
They're the wounded.
Then it's not so bad.
I'm so afraid that
the dead are carried around.
Amin, received, understood.
Roger, Amin.
- Are you often bombed here?
Yesterday, no.
00:59:29,305 --> 00:59:29,280
- Yesterday, no.
The day before yesterday,
it hit behind the raspberries.
And three days ago, behind the kitchen.
Come and have a look.
Come and see. I'll show you.
- Thank you so much. God bless you!
- You're welcome.
00:59:50,305 --> 00:59:50,280
You're welcome.
It's good to have it all in boxes.
We'll figure it out, I'll get Nina and Nadia.
We'll divide it all up for 26 people.
Thank you very much.
Come on, I'll show you.
There's a big pit there.
See the craters there?
- Why don't you leave?
- Where to?
They've already gone,
those who had transport and money.
It's my...
dream not to die, not to be killed.
I ask God, 'God, help us survive.
Help end this war, so they stop shooting.'
And this killing! Ukraine and Russia,
you're brothers. Why kill each other?
That's how things are.
Of course, we're all for Russia.
Well, a guy on Lenin St., Vitka,
he had a store and always spoke out,
but he's gone somewhere.
And why are people for Russia?
I don't know. You see, I went to school...
We had a portrait of Lenin
hanging over the blackboard.
It said: 'study, study, study,
as Great Lenin willed.'
Ukraine is against Lenin!
We studied everything Russian.
Our class represented Kazakhstan,
one of our 15 Republics.
Each class put on concerts
and wore their national dress.
We should be friends in peace,
we should be friends.
I was used to it, I studied it...
I believed in it all!
I usually walk with two sticks,
but now I have one.
My knees are gone.
I worked in the mine for 28 years.
I'll find a flashlight.
My son sleeps here on this cot
made of bricks and planks.
You've been here a year?
Since March, the end of March.
Yes, a year.
I blame...
It was America that got involved, I think.
Well, Ukraine joining NATO or whatever.
God forbid Ukraine breaks through here.
That scares me a lot.
I think Ukraine will kill us all.
For talking to Russia, and so on.
I think we'll never make peace
with Ukraine.
Never.
Mikhailovna!
Let's go back, in case we have
to hide in the basement.
This stove probably hadn't
been cleaned for a year.
I miss home.
I miss my buddies.
My garden was awesome...
and the vineyards were kick-ass!
The weekends...
a day would start with a trip...
to amusement parks with the children.
And ended...
with a barbecue in the yard with friends.
Yeah, those were really good times.
In 2014, when Ukrainian forces
began bombing Donetsk, it was brutal.
I drove out with my children
under shelling.
I drove out with
children
Of course, Donetsk rosee up.
Most men joined the [separatist] militia.
I spent roughly 3 months in the militia.
Now, there's no life in Donetsk.
Now everyone's scattered.
Some killed...
some somewhere.
...of NATO caliber, 155 mm.
Yasinovataya (Donetsk region) and
Panteleimonovka village were also hit.
I came here to help people.
To protect them.
Maybe this nightmare they've been
living in since 2014 would end.
But the reality wasn't
at all what I expected.
Where did you find
a patriotic newspaper?
They bring them.
Red Star-
Basically, propaganda.
- Our Spiritual Weapon:
Our Ancestors' Military Tradition -
In fact, what's written
and shown on TV isn't real.
It's dangerous because
after watching TV, I volunteered...
let's say, as a patriot, for this SMO
[Special Military Operation].
I volunteered for six months.
Now I'm already
in my seventh month here.
They said the only way
back to Russia is 'feet first' [dead).
If I'd known that, I wouldn't have come.
If l'd known that, I wouldn't have come.
Because I too had life plans.
There's no forward movement.
I think the conflict is artificially prolonged.
Because it benefits someone.
We don't want war.
We don't want to kill, or to die.
What do you think you'll do?
Keep on serving.
Neither they [Ukrainians) nor we have a choice.
The tanks rumbled on the field.
Soldiers went into their last battle.
And a young commander,
with his head bashed in,
was carried out.
Happy Birthday, bro!
Pour champagne on it,
like when you buy a family car!
I kind of spilled an energy drink in here.
So much shit! You're scared
to press anything and fuck it up.
Look, press the rangefinder with
your index finger. Here's the 'SCT.'
They didn't even explain what it is.
They just said, 'You'll need it', that's it.
Fuck, it's a USSR label.
Even though it's 2023 in Russia.
Cartoon, fire!
Come on, start up your baby!
When we arrived, at first there was fear.
And then somehow it didn't matter.
What you want or don't want isn't a thing.
Here, have to' means 'have to'.
Here, 'have to means 'have to'.
I don't see the concept of
fair or unfair here.
They and we shell each other
almost the same.
- When did the shooting start?
- At 10:30.
-Whoa!
Incoming, incoming.
I told you, fuck. Get down...
Nastia, come in, please.
- Coming, coming.
Something's on fire.
No, nothing's burning.
Now they'll adjust and hit again.
Now they'll reload
and start again.
Oh, fuck.
- It's a cannon if it takes time to reload.
01:50:06,985 --> 01:12:51,960
- Oh, fuck.
01:12:51,985 --> 01:12:51,960
It's a cannon if it takes time to reload.
They're adjusting.
It's coming!
2 minutes!
They're clearly hitting the house.
That was three.
The doors must be shut.
- No!
- Bricks will fly in.
01:13:12,025 --> 01:13:09,960
No!
Bricks will fly in.
Or let's get the fuck out.
- We can't go anywhere now.
- There's a bird [drone] up there.
01:13:15,865 --> 01:13:15,240
There's a bird [drone] up there.
Ours are fucking quiet.
They'll start late, as usual.
It's not like this in the trenches.
It's easier to handle there.
Shit. We lived a good life.
We all move out today.
Fuck, didn't you smoke
enough outside?
We're suffocating in here.
Ready. Ready. Ready...
It's not for us.
No, that was closer.
- It's a long way off.
- Probably a tank.
A mass grave.
- Where are you going? Stay.
- Give me a smoke.
Hey, what are you, an addict?
Now it's closer again.
Where are you going? Smoke in here.
Ready!
It's a tank! I tell you, damn it.
A cannon can't fire that fast.
Listen. Maybe it's ours?
Ours are totally silent.
These are ours.
- Ours, ours...
How fucking long did it take them?
20 minutes passed.
Quiet, quiet. It's a birdie [drone]!
Quiet!
A bee!
Still, it was buzzing.
- It's a hornet.
- Yes, they sound the same.
Let's see now.
OK, I'm off.
- It's OK.
- At intervals, two at a time.
Good, let's go now.
Sure, let's go.
I wake up each morning and think
of the guys lying in the ground.
They won't see the sun,
or the sky, won't see or talk
to their parents.
Starting a war is very easy.
But to finish it, try doing that.
Was it scary?
Are we fucking off?
- Yes, yes. Let's fuck off!
Anastasia, get in.
- Altitude, 57.
- So guys, ready to party?
- We're ready.
Time to prepare?
7 minutes.
Aim and report when ready.
- Copy.
46... 640.
An anti-tank launcher is firing at us.
Confirm, 46... 640... 46... 640...
It didn't kill you?
Nope.
What command?!
There was no command!
Fuck! You're crazy.
It could've killed us!
Fire, fire!
Spikey, Mario and Chemist.
Are these all yours? Over.
Yes, all mine, all mine.
200, for sure?
Three 200s?
No one can get to them yet, over.
Tire, Amin receiving.
Say again, three 200s?
Three 200s from the medical unit.
No one can get to them yet. Over.
Fuck this shit!
Left here.
Pull over at the barrier.
There's a fucking war going on here.
Swat! Let me in!
- Look, he's actually aiming his gun.
- Yeah, right.
That's my unit for fuck's sake, Swat!
Please.
Please, let me in alone, at least.
Don't fucking shoot, fuck.
Fucking military.
What a clusterfuck.
Get the fuck back in there!
This is how it fucking is.
What a joke.
Circus, huh?
You're like kids, fuck.
May 1?
A great time to argue.
Go right!
Mario's fucked up.
Fucking morons.
A little closer to you.
Amin, let's go.
It turns out one was left.
Anton was left behind.
They said one didn't die right away.
Spikey died instantly,
did you see his neck?
Wind, Amin, let's go!
Guys, go. They'll see us and fire.
Let's go.
Fucking Polish mortar.
You don't hear it coming.
It killed three with one hit.
I'm most sorry for Chemist.
He said he was scared.
It was his first day. His first time.
The first!
One day he came to me and said:
"Damn...
Life was just starting to get good,
it was all fine.
Life with my wife was amazing,
work was great, just like a fairy tale.
Then war comes along and I'm drafted.'
Fuck.
Hello?
I'm calling about your husband.
He died on Sunday.
My condolences to you.
I'm in command of a medical unit,
he was in my unit.
I don't know when they'll call officially,
so I'm calling you myself.
A shell flew in.
Three people died at once.
He died on the spot.
Be strong.
My condolences.
I'm sorry.
Is it far?
Another 2 kilometres.
Give me a cigarette too.
God willing, it will all be fine.
They said that yesterday too.
Three 200s.
DI
I'm not here.
My personnel file is lost.
No salary...
I'm not on the unit list.
They said, 'Keep serving' and 'good-bye.'
Strawberries will be here soon.
The bags are fucking white.
Keep your distance.
So that if anyone gets hit,
the others won't.
They're close.
500 metres.
They shout...
'Russians, surrender!'
'Occupiers.'
'Occupiers!' Fuck you in the ass!
The Russian anthem is played
at full blast on the loudspeaker at 5 am.
What do they play for us?
They play the Ukrainian anthem.
Well, let's just mark it out.
We should dig the trenches faster.
Is that a bird (drone] flying?
No, it's the river.
For the last two months,
I got nothing for being on the front line.
I didn't get my additional pay
after I was wounded either.
So when your contract ends,
you'll get drafted?
Mine ended two months ago already.
Everyone's has.
01:28:46,800 --> 01:28:46,320
- Mine ended two months ago already.
Idon't...
How much did you get this month?
I got nothing.
My family... they were threatened
with eviction if they didn't pay.
Yesterday, I borrowed some money
from the drafted boys.
If I'd known this would happen,
I'd be damned if l'd have signed up.
What a situation...
I don't give a damn.
I need money.
It's the only way.
I can't say anything now.
I can't think until I'm home.
But I think, 100%, it'll drag me back.
It's a strange pull.
I can't describe it, but it's there.
It's a kind of habit.
Thanks.
Can you imagine? I forgot what floor.
You forgot your floor?
forgot which floor.
I think the 12th.
Please come in.
For abandoning the front,
llya risks criminal prosecution.
But because he's 50,
he might get written off.
Hi.
Daddy!
My pretty little thing.
Hi, sleepyhead.
Meanwhile, the battalion
is moved to a tougher front.
We've been hit. Film this!
- Film it!
- What happened?
We got our asses kicked a bit.
I'm fucked if I'll ride
by that window again!
Can you believe it?
How lucky you are!
The glass is gone!
'Fuckin' eh!', I thought.
They moved the whole
brigade overnight to Bakhmut.
It's the toughest front.
The Bakhmut front.
It almost killed me, and I'm happy.
This tire got slashed.
It's so confusing here,
I don't even know what we're fighting for.
Not even a clue.
I've seen so much here
over these 10 months.
Now, I just want to go home.
Where no one shoots or kills anyone.
Quiet, peace.
But there's no option.
I'm willing to give my life formy country.
I'm a Russian patriot.
Yes, I'm a patriot.
A lot has changed here...
Many have died, many wounded,
and a change of command.
The new commander, I am told, is against my presence.
But he doesn't live here with the troops,
so I should be able to avoid him
and film a bit longer.
He is carved out of flint and steel.
Brilliant.
I watched it and just cried.
Soviet movies had
the biggest influence on me.
The values there
were very patriotic, I'd say.
01:35:04,825 --> 01:35:04,800
were very patriotic, l'd say.
There was no cynicism.
Unlike now.
Dear friends, thank you
for your service to Russia.
I talk to locals and some think
the Soviet Union will return.
But it won't! It won't.
01:35:23,185 --> 01:35:22,920
KAE
...to protect our ideals,
culture and national interests...
Here, I feel disgust, realising that
I don't understand what it's all for.
...to do everything
for the sake of their beloved country.
Anastasia, stop filming.
- Will you marry me?
- What the..?
Please. I'm at a loss. Fuck!
Are you serious?
Come to me, I can't.
was so nervous!
Comrade husband, that was unexpected.
I remember when
we first filmed, and I said...
I wouldn't have a family,
that I'd devote my life to the army.
Who knew? He was already
in our unit, sitting in the medic van.
Who knew?
Ah, you're here!
I don't know,
I was so scared, they prepared me.
I have a different attitude now
to family, and to having children later.
It's beautiful.
My hands are shaking,
why are they are shaking?
Nightmare!
So my family is my homeland now.
We're cleaning up
and going on an offensive.
Probably tonight.
- How does it feel?
01:37:57,625 --> 01:37:56,880
How does it feel?
I'm not going, am I crazy?
To die out there.
I'm not trained for assault.
I'm a medic anyway.
They're sending us to die.
- Die where?
- They're sending us to die.
Assaulting.
Klecheevka, in the woods there.
There's no exact plan on the enemy,
on mine clearance.
01:41:58,345 --> 01:38:31,800
There's no
plan on the enemy,
They're sending us in with
our eyes closed, like blind kittens.
We hope for the best.
- Are you ready to risk your life for...?
- No, I'm not ready to risk my life, I'm not.
To be honest, no, l'm not ready.
But...
I can't refuse, because...
If I must, I must.
And you can't argue with that.
The guys say it's fucked up out there.
It's targeted.
When people go in, they get shot at.
From all sides, both sides.
People are being killed in droves
and they don't care.
and they don't care. ,
Guys, let's take it off.
Announcement:
breakfast is ready in the kitchen.
What breakfast? Lunch!
Yes, I apologise, lunch.
I'm all messed up,
days, breakfasts, dinners...
So you check...
For 120 points without a lucky hand
you must collect all cards.
Fuck, it's hard, I've already forgotten.
One of these should work for you.
When you get it, it's a cool process.
I always thought of Ukrainian people
as brotherly people.
My roots are in Ukraine,
actually in the West.
While politicians work out
who has the bigger balls,
there will be many victims.
It's time to finish this, enough is enough.
Let the enemy go home alive
and well to their families, and us too.
I saw so many guys that weren't
retrieved from near Klecheevka.
We walked over these corpses.
There are more bodies here.
More bodies. They're ours.
This one. I don't know whose.
This is ours, with the red.
He's all black. Fuck.
They're all ours...
strewn around.
He's been here a while.
That's ours too.
A God forbid, God forbid.
"I tell you, God forbid!
We don't say 'no',
but so far, we're all against it.
For the first time,
I see the guys on edge.
Almost no one's seen
Ukrainians face-to-face.
All this time they've been defensive like
WWI soldiers in trenches and dugouts.
Tomorrow will be their first offensive.
- I'm going to shoot them in the legs.
Max, enough.
Brother, you can call me
the last of the blabbermouths.
Max, stop the hysteria.
- I fucking can't, P.O.
You get hysterical.
You think no one else gets it?
Well, fuck!
We're being sent in to slaughter.
You do know that, right?
Uncle, Uncle... Are you going?
- Uncle, are you going?
- I'm going, is there a choice?
We're going, no?
Why armour? No bullet can get you.
It's for shrapnel, not bullets.
Cedar, do you have any pain killers?
- Yes.
You got another tourniquet?
-Yes.
No, you fucking don't.
Whoever got in, help the others.
Victory will be ours!
Minus One, Minus One,
this is Azimuth. Over.
Azimuth, receiving.
Situation report?
We're moving slowly
No sign of the enemy yet.
We're moving slowly.
Did the shelling stop?
Rain continues, rain continues.
Minus One, another incoming.
Minus One, another coming at us.
A machine gun is firing towards us.
They've made contact in quadrant 11.
An APC has been hit
in the woods, left flank.
Why can't you get in there?
Fucking bitch.
I'm sending help your way now.
- Come on, Godspeed!
- Thank you, Comrade Moscow.
They took your soldier
with a severed leg.
Blown up by a mine.
Is Fox in place?
Fox is 300.
Are his troops in place?
Fighters on the left flank rolled back.
The "dill" [slur for Ukrainians] came in,
they ran from there.
Did the "dill" take it?
Anyway, the left flank withdrew.
The "dill" advanced,
fucking shelled everything.
Quickly, quickly!
Rapid assist to evacuate the wounded,
and ready the men to assault.
No one can move yet.
They're firing cluster bombs.
I'm hit, I'm hit.
You're wounded?
I don't know what's up with my arm.
So far, so good.
Now it's like a fucking nuclear
bomb was dropped on us.
It went off pretty bad.
I need more people here,
a kind of reserve.
Who's 200?
Ilgiz and Valera and Tatar.
- They didn't get Valera out yet?
- Not yet, Valera's still there.
Did you see Valera or not?
Not yet. They didn't get him out yet.
They've been carrying wounded all night.
300s, 200s.
Trucks full of wounded or dead...
To the hospital?
They yell at us in the O.R.
Ilgiz had his legs blown off?
I don't know what to
write to Ilgiz's mother.
01:50:13,585 --> 01:50:12,000
don't know what to
What can you write?
You can't make anything up.
Let Pasha do it, you're the commander.
I should?
You should call and talk to her.
You mean on the phone?
Commander, take command!
Wait.
Valera has three children.
Cedar's alive.
Tatar's lying there.
Cat shot himself.
He shot himself?
His spine was severed.
He wouldn't make it, couldn't crawl.
He was surrounded and shot himself.
Dudik's legs were broken.
He said, 'Better you shoot me
than I crawl.'
He stayed there.
He's probably 200.
- With you, I believe in love.
Waiting for you. I love you. -
- I miss you. May this piece of me
and home be your talisman. -
The escorting tank was hit
on the first approach.
Then the enemy artillery began to work.
We were getting shelled
from three sides.
We had no support. Nothing.
I heard Cat's words...
01:53:47,425 --> 01:53:47,280
Theard Cat's words...
"guys, I'm fucked...
my legs have failed."
The front needs to be cleaned.
Ew, what a smell.
I took shrapnel in my back.
A grenade was thrown at me
from a bird [drone].
from a bird [drone]
After that it reloaded and
threw a drone grenade at me.
Just where a guy sat.
The hole is where his legs were.
pretended to be dead, I won't deny it.
I heard the "hohols" [slur for Ukrainians]
walk around at night.
T heard the "hohols" [slur for Ukrainians)
I heard the "hohols" (slur for Ukrainians]
Theard the "hohols" [slur for Ukrainians]
Crawling...
1 prayed to all the Gods.
I asked them to keep me alive.
For strength, to get out of there.
I got out.
What can I say? It's a just war after all.
Very just.
If we weren't there, there's no telling
what would happen to our Russia.
The enemy would listen to the West.
And under this leadership,
they'd besiege our borders.
And we can't allow that.
So...
When did you reach that conclusion?
I came to that conclusion a while back,
after being wounded, and now home
in peacetime, on Russian territory...
think it's right that we're there.
- But you thought differently before?
- Yes.
- For world peace
want peace, for the whole world.
I want peace, for the whole world.
You think in a more militant way now,
why is that?
Why's that?
Because I'll never forget the faces
of those who were with me at the start.
I'll never forget.
They were dying.
There's this video.
This is the enemy's Telegram channel.
I feel guilty.
Because I couldn't save my friends.
Oh, my son...
Oh, how hard it is...
I raised him, I taught him...
I had nothing good for myself...
So we come here.
Why do we need this glory?
What will we tell our grandchildren?
What can I say about him?
Why did he fight?
Though he said that we'd win,
he probably didn't understand
who we were fighting, or what for.
A baffling war, it's baffling for everyone.
Here, Amin.
Here is where he lies.
You know he was so afraid to go there.
He told everyone,
'I won't come back from there.'
My darling...
How I love you.
You see who came to visit?
Anastasia and your commander.
Honestly, who really needs this war?
Maybe someone needs it.
But not us: wives, mothers and children.
I give permission for this video
to be used in a documentary.
I don't mind.
Let our Russia, and the people,
know what's going on in our world.
It's so hard...
All young.
How many are there? How many?
All so young...
And he loved all baked foods.
Let it be there. I'll put it here.
Eat it, my son.
Eat, Mom gave it to you.
I now have many friends here.
They weren't superhuman, or evil.
The war machine
dragged many to the front,
exploiting their sense of patriotism,
friendship and financial need.
In the end, here lie the ordinary people
on whose bones big politics is made.
Hold on, cutie pie.
Now we'll clean you up.
Well, what can I do?
You spilled the hot water.
You didn't have to spill it.
Shush... come on.
Be patient!
Cold, huh?
This whole thing
just came out of the blue.
And now...
it's very serious.
After all, a child is such a responsibility.
How did you feel when you
found out you were pregnant?
It's a strange feeling, I don't know.
It's not joy, it's something strange.
Fear, sort of...
So much fear.
You have to bring him up,
put all the best into him, so he
grows up to be a decent, good person.
It's not easy.
What will you tell him about ...
The war?
- Yes.
I don't want to tell my child anything
about it, I don't want to at all.
Because...
90% of it is all lies.
And it's all...
How shall I put it...
He wouldn't understand all these things.
He won't understand that some
people at the top are making money.
And others die.
That'll be hard to understand
and explain to a child.
How do you explain that to a child?
Teach him the history
of the Russian Empire.
Which princes ruled.
Let him learn that...
But what's going on now...
It's all very...
I don't know how I'll explain it all.